Now, today's דף *Daf* is יא *Yud Aleph*. Pick up with some
משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah* at the top. We just got through a whole
story of talking cows, so it's going to be anything from this
point down is going to be more normal.
Right. But we have introduced the idea of somebody saying, I'm a
נזיר nazir *Nazir* from X, and the X is not Y. And
that was the interesting debate of בית הלל *Beis Hillel*, בית שמאי
*Beis Shammai*, and רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda*'s interpretation of בית שמאי *Beis
Shammai*, whether you are a נזיר nazir. *Nazir*, you're nothing, or you're
forbidding the the X, the meat or the whatever, the dates upon
yourself, but you're not actually becoming a נזיר nazir *Nazir*. Let's take
a look at our משנה Mishna *Mishnah* where we get back to
normal נזירות nezirot, *Nezirus*. מזגו לו lo את הכוס *Mazgu lo es
hakos*. So, כחנא בן שואלו *Kehana ben She'alo*. No. So, for anybody
who knows, that's the introduction in the משנה Mishna, *Mishnah* to the
to the ארבע כוסות *Arba Kosos*. It says they pour they pour
the כוס kos *kos* and then you ask the ארבע כוסות *Arba
Kosos* and ask and you ask the four questions on the סדר
*Seder* night. Anyway, but no. מזגו לו את הכוס *Mazgu lo es
hakos*, so they mixed they somebody's pouring a cup of wine for
you. ואמר v'amar *Ve'amar*, and the and you and the person said,
הריני נזיר Hareini Nazir, ממנו mimenu *Harei ni nazir mimenu*, I am
a נזיר nazir *Nazir* from it. Okay. Now, so here you're saying
from it, which is something that is wine, so which works for
נזירות nezirot, *Nezirus*. On the other hand, maybe you mean only from
this one cup and maybe you don't really mean to be a
נזיר nazir *Nazir* and it's just your way of saying that you're
not going to drink this cup of wine. So nevertheless, הרי זה
נזיר harei zeh nazir, *Harei zeh nazir*. I'm sorry. If you say
you are a נזיר nazir. *Nazir* from wine, even if you say
from it, which might mean from this cup of wine, there even
בית הלל *Beis Hillel* agrees that that is a נזיר nazir, *Nazir*.
And I'll remind you that we had the position and debate earlier.
If somebody says I'm I'm a נזיר nazir *Nazir* from wine, I'm
a נזיר nazir. *Nazir* from haircuts, I'm a נזיר nazir *Nazir* from
this. Even if you mention only one part of the נזירות nezirot
*Nezirus*, it's basically all or nothing. There's an opinion that says it's
nothing, but the position of the חכמים Chachamim *Chachamim* is is that
no, it's all. Once you say you're a נזיר nazir *Nazir* from
a part of what נזירות nezirot. *Nezirus* is about, you're a נזיר
nazir *Nazir* from the whole thing. And therefore, this is interpreted here
that again, even though you're talking about a specific and a concrete
cup of wine, or that seems to be the case, although you
could say ממנו *mimenu* means from it, from wine, right, from not
from it, from this particular cup. I mean, I guess it would
be an interesting question if you said הריני נזיר מן הכוס הזה
hareini nazir min hakos hazeh *Harei ni nazir min hakos hazeh* or
מן הכוס היין hayayin הזה *min hakos hayayin hazeh* or something like
that. Okay, so that would be interesting. ממנו *Mimenu* is a little
ambiguous. So we are reading it because it's about wine and it's
a piece of נזירות nezirot *Nezirus*, you're a נזיר nazir *Nazir* from
everything. But now we're about to see that context matters. Okay. מעשה
maaseh באשה b'isha אחת achas. *Maaseh be-isha achas*, there's a story with
a particular woman שהייתה שיכורה *she-haysah shikora*, she was drunk, ומזגו לה
את הכוס *u-mazgu lah es hakos*, and they were giving her another
glass of wine to drink. ואמרה *Ve'amrah*, and she said, הריני Hareini,
נזירה ממנו *Harei ni nezirah mimenu*, I am a נזירה *nezirah* from
it. אמרו חכמים chachamim *Amru Chachamim*, the sages said, לא lo נתכוונה
זו אלא לומר הרי harei הוא hu עלי alai כקרבן kekorban. *lo
nis-kavnah zo ela lomar harei hu alai k'korban*. No, all she's saying
is that this cup of wine is forbidden to me like by
a נדר neder *neder*, by a קונם *konam*. She did not mean
to say that she is actually accepting נזירות nezirot, *Nezirus* from wine;
she meant specifically this cup. So you see that context matters. But
the question is, why is the context of the second case any
different than the context of the first case? So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is going to ask that question. The other thing to point
out is, you know, they tell a this is like this, you
know, this is like a standard ישיבה *Yeshiva* joke, so I don't
know if it's really funny or not. But anyway, but it's like,
you know, the somebody comes into the ישיבה *Yeshiva*, a big rabbi
goes visits the ישיבה *Yeshiva* and he says what's everybody learning? Oh,
they're learning מסכת נזיר nazir *Maseches Nazir*. So he says, can a
woman be a נזיר nazir *Nazir*? So everybody's like, wait, wait, wait,
I think there's a רש"י *Rashi* somewhere, I think it's I think
somewhere on דף *Daf* somewhere I can find whatever. And everybody's looking
for a source of whether a woman can be a נזיר nazir?
*Nazir*. And he says, it's a פשיטא *pshita*! איש או אשה כי
יפליא לנדור נדר neder נזיר nazir *Ish o isha ki yafli lindor
neder nazir*. The funny thing about that is, is that actually there's
a lot of very explicit discussions of women becoming a נזיר nazir
*Nazir*. From last the last מסכת *Maseches* had a woman becoming a
נזיר nazir *Nazir* and her husband being מיפר *meifer* it, right? And
so that came up a lot in the discussions of הפרה *hafarah*.
And right right here you have a whole little story about a
woman or whatever accepting נזירות nezirot *Nezirus*. So it's interesting to note
that, you know, that's not only in the פסוקים *Pesukim*, it's actually
you know it's true because it's not only in the פסוקים *Pesukim*,
it's in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. So anyway, yes. She can't have
intention.
That could be. I mean, there's a question about how drunk is
drunk. You know, there's a whole story about הלכה Halacha *Halacha* about
that, that I mean there's a whole question, right? But at what
stage are you so drunk that you're not considered responsible for your
actions? And yes, there does to get to be a stage, רמב"ם
*Rambam* in one place said when somebody gets to the level of
שכרותו של לוט *Shichruso shel Lot*, as drunk as Lot was. You
know, I mean at what so there is a question, like when
is that threshold? I mean you know, but but here because
the חכמים chachamim *Chachamim* say לא נתכוונה אלא לומר *lo nis-kavnah ela
lomar*.
Right. It's a question about כוונה *kavana*, exactly. So that's right, exactly.
Right, right, right. That is clearly not the case here. They're not
saying she was not able to have right intention or right mind.
She's saying she meant something else. But yes, so so thank you,
yes. That is correct. But there are stages when you get to
be so drunk that you're not considered responsible for your actions, but
that's not what's being talked about here. Yes.
My question is, to the extent that we learned in נדרים nedarim
*Nedarim* that פירושן להקל perushan lehakel. *perushan le-hakel* for סתם stam נדרים
Nedarim *stam nedarim*. נזירות nezirot *Nezirus* is a type of נדר neder
*neder*, so would you apply that same thing here? Like the other
person said הריני נזיר Hareini Nazir, ממנו *Harei ni nazir mimenu*, and
then you think you're נזיר nazir *Nazir* but the person comes and
says I know, I only really meant...
Yeah, look, so I think that that's I understand what you're saying.
Look, I think it's a good question because on the one hand,
even in נדרים Nedarim. *Nedarim* where we say פירושן להקל perushan lehakel,
*perushan le-hakel* that you could accept... explain ambiguous phrases,
we read major סוגיות sugyos
where we didn't ask the guy what he meant and we just
decided what he meant, you know? So, I think when do you
say that you get to explain what you mean and when do
you not remains a bit of a question mark back in מסכת
נדרים, Masechet Nedarim, and here while in principle I would agree to
say we say the basic principle of פיו ולבו שוין, piv velibo
shavin, you know, we have yet to introduce that concept here. Until
now the whole discussion has been we're not—you know, there was one
place actually where the גמרא Gemara. mentioned about the guy said "this
is what I meant," right? But, and you know, so we did
have that once. I didn't use the phrase פירושן להקל. perushan lehakel,
But overall we don't really start by asking the guy, you know,
we start by asking ourselves what it meant.
But would we say פירושן להקל, you think, potentially?
I don't know, it remains a big question. The גמרא Gemara introduced
that idea and then in like eighty percent of the סוגיות sugyos
completely, you know, decided we're going to figure out what he meant.
So, you know, it remains an ongoing question, right, about this issue
of פיו ולבו שוין piv velibo shavin and how much do we
A, ask you what it means to understand what your פה peh
meant or what the words actually say, and B, even if we've
decided the words said one thing, but if you tell us but
that wasn't what I was intending or thinking, so maybe I said
it but that wasn't what I wanted to say, right, that would
be אין פיו ולבו שוין. ein piv velibo shavin. It also shouldn't
be binding. So in principle if we took those two ideas seriously,
פיו ולבו שוין piv velibo shavin and פירושן להקל, we could do
away with eighty percent of these סוגיות and just say, well let's
just ask the guy. What do those words mean? What were you
thinking? Whatever. I understand. All right. Well, clearly context does matter here,
but you're right, it's more context than asking her. So, and we'll
see the issue of context in the גמרא. Gemara But you're right
to raise the question, but you know, we should also recognize at
the same time that the גמרא Gemara. seems to mostly not say
you know, we're not going to go there, we're going to figure
out more objectively what's going on. Yeah.
So the standard reading of this is that we're giving context that
because she was drunk she
wanted—Ah, so that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say, yeah.
However one could also read it that a person who's drunk can't
express themselves very well
and—Oh, that's interesting.
So it's as if the חכמים chachamim are saying this is the
excuse for her not being
precise.
That's interesting. So that the words themselves should not be read as
precisely when somebody, right, when somebody is drunk they speak a little
bit—okay, well let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara Because the
גמרא Gemara is going to ask, like how do you have a
case afterwards that contradicts the previous one? What's the difference between the
two? So the גמרא Gemara says: מעשה לסתור? maaseh listor? You're bringing
a case in order to contradict the rule? אמרת רישא, amarta reisha,
in the beginning you say הרי זה נזיר, harei zeh nazir. that
the person would be a נזיר nazir in that case. והדר תני
מעשה באשה אחת, vehadar tani maaseh beishah achas, and then you tell
me this story about this woman. אלמא בהאי הוא דאסור, alma behai
hu de’assur, בהאי הוא דאסור, behai hu de’assur, היין אחרינא שרי, hayayin
achrina shari, it's this one cup is what you're forbidding yourself, other
wine is permissible. Not just other
wine, you're not
a נזיר. nazir, So the גמרא gemara. says: חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני.
chasorei mechasra vehachi katani. All right, some words are missing. We've got
to stick in the transition sentence that explains why this story is
different. Okay, and here's what it has to say: מדקתני כוס אמר
הריני נזיר ממנו הרי זה נזיר. midekatani cos amar hareini nazir mimenu
harei zeh nazir. If you say I am a נזיר nazir from
it, you know, from then you're a נזיר nazir from this cup.
Okay. ואם שכור הוא, ve’im shikur hu, but if you were drunk,
ואמר הריני נזיר ממנו, ve’amar hareini nazir mimenu, I am a נזיר
nazir from it, אינו נזיר. eino nazir. Why not? מאי טעמא? mai
taama? Now notice by the way the shift to Aramaic. So it's
not saying that this מאי טעמא mai taama is in the—is what
they're trying to read into the
משנה, Mishna. the גמרא's gemara just sort of now explicating what the
reason would be.
מאי טעמא? mai taama? כמאן דאמר הרי עלי קרבן הוא. keman de’amar
harei alai korban hu. Because in that case it's like he said
this is forbidden to me as a קרבן, korban, so the wine
is forbidden, not that I'm a
נזיר. nazir וכי תימא לימא הכי—and vechi seima leima hachi if you
say well if the guy just wanted to say the wine is
forbidden to me as a קרבן, korban, not that he's a נזיר,
nazir. so say those words! Say this wine is כקרבן. k'korban, No.
סבר, savar, he thinks, מייתינא אחרינא ומצערי לי. meitina achrina umitza'aru li.
If I just say this wine is forbidden to me as a
קרבן, korban, they're not going to leave me alone, they're going to
try to give me another—another glass of wine to drink. I want
to sort of, you know, go cold turkey and everybody's pressuring me
to drink and the wine is flowing and if I just say
I won't drink this one cup they're not going to stop it.
So, what am I going to do?
אימא להו המילתא. eima lehu hamiltha. I'll say look, I'm a נזיר
nazir, from this wine. That makes it clear like I—I don't want
anything to do with it. דפסקה להו, depaska lehu, that's like absolute,
they get the idea like I don't want any wine. ומעשה נמי
באשה אחת, umaaseh nami beishah achas, and guess what we have a
story that a woman that she was drunk and in the case
of being drunk you want to use a phrase that sounds more
categorical and absolute so people don't—you know, people don't keep on trying—nobody's
asking you for your car keys, what they're doing is they're trying
to just get you more drunk. Okay, and you want to actually...
actually put a stop to it and that תוספות Tosfos actually says
an interesting thing. If you look at תוספות, Tosfos, it says it
says:
לישנא דשיכורא הוא הוא אומר הרי עלי כקרבן. Lishna d'shikora hu hu
omer harei alai k'korban. תוספות Tosfos פירש peirash שדרך she'derech בני b'nei
אדם adam להפציר l'haftzir בשיכור b'shikor שישתה. she'yishteh. It's a lot of
fun. Here's a guy who's drunk, let's get him more drunk. We'll
all have a good laugh at his expense, okay? And he'll do
stupid things. ואיהו v'ihu אינו eino רוצה rotzeh לשתות, lishtos, but he
doesn't want to. Okay, so everybody's pressuring him to drink. The only
way he's going to get them to lay off is if he
uses this type of a word of a נזיר. nazir And one
still wonders like why don't you just say הרי כל kol היין
you know, in this in this house is אסור asur עלי כקרבן,
but again, you know, maybe nevertheless you want to really communicate the
sense of like... yeah, that word exactly has some power and it
means like leave him alone, you know, okay, we're going to stop
we're going to stop pressuring you. But clear but anyway here's where
context does matter. It's not though what you suggested that if you're
drunk you're not being as precise with your word choice. Here actually
דוקא davka you're being specifically precise. You want to use a word
that's going to get a certain message across. But you do see
context matters. What you don't see is so if a guy said
this cup of wine, I'm a נזיר nazir from this cup of
wine, maybe that would be different as opposed to saying ממנו which
could be more generic. Yeah, Jenna?
Could you become a נזיר nazir while you're drunk? I mean not
from the thing we're talking about of a preciseness, but like if
you're drunk and you're a נזיר nazir then you're automatically not...
Yeah, but you're not... a נזיר nazir is not allowed to be
drunk, he's not allowed to drink. Right. Now, the question is can
you be a נזיר nazir if you're standing in a cemetery? Right?
So we'll actually get to that, but that might, you know, but
that's not necessarily impossible. Yeah.
More general, just what what is the status of something you say
when you're drunk?
Well, that goes back to David's question. So like I said, there's
a discussion in הלכה Halacha about this. It's important in general in
הלכה because it gets to the question about, you know, about like
state of mind and, you know, there could be multiple reasons why
a person isn't in total control of their faculties and to what
degree do we say that they're responsible for their actions and so
on. Now, what I think is interesting is, let's say I don't
know somebody is מחלל mechallel שבת Shabbos when they're drunk, okay? Or
they damage property when they're drunk, okay, אדם adam מועד muad לעולם,
l'olam, but other types of things. Okay, that's one thing. You did
an action and if you're not at least completely have lost control
of your, you know, you know, of your rational faculties, then you'd
still be responsible even if you're not fully like, you know, even
you know even if you're a little bit, you know, out of
control. But the question is would the same be true by issues
of הפלאה? hafla'ah? Because the questions of נדר neder, and a נזיר
nazir are issues about, you know, speech. This is what we were
talking about before, פיו piv ולבו v'libo שוין. shavin. It's fundamentally is
not, you know, it's an act of speech, but it's an act
of speech expressing thought. And if it's something that ultimately is rooted
in what you're thinking and your ability to think clearly has been
clouded, right, it's an interesting question about maybe being drunk actually does
more say you cannot sue a נדר neder than it would say
you're not responsible for an act you do, right? An act you
do you have the physical reality of the act and the fact
that as long as you're not totally, you know, totally lost your
faculties, maybe you're still responsible as opposed to something of this. So
it's an interesting question to ask. Maybe the degree of drunkenness that
sort of exempts you would be different in the area of נדרים
nedarim and נזיר? nazir I haven't seen that, I'm just speculating, but
I do know that there is a lot of הלכתי Halachic literature
about how drunk a person has to be before they're considered to
be no longer responsible for their actions. Yes.
In this סוגיא, sugya, I find peculiar. חסורי chisorei מחסרא mechasra and
the explanation are together longer than the משנה Mishna. itself.
What's bothering the בבלי Bavli so much about this?
I understand what's bothering. Same thing bothers all of us, that the
משנה, mishna. the story contradicts the first part. The fact that it
really... the real question is not what's bothering, the real question is
how you prepared to so completely rewrite the משנה. mishna. But my
answer would be look, there's a general question about חסורי chisorei מחסרא,
mechasra, which is does it really mean that it's saying that the
text was missing and this really was restoring the original text, or
is it actually saying like you know, no, you have to implicitly
understand that there's something else going on at the end? It wasn't
part of the text, but it was implicit, okay, and that's that
I would sort of more say is the case here. All right,
let's go on look at the next משנה.
mishna, And use the word אבל.
aval.
אבל aval
מעשה באשה אחת. Yeah, but that would basically more say like there's
two different הלכות, Halachos, like it's a מחלוקת, machlokes, right?
But this also goes on and ואיהו v'eihu אינו eino שיכור. shikor.
But that would also explain the first part.
What if you're not drunk then they're not going to...
All right, Michael wants us to read the end of the תוספות
Tosfos which helps explain why you're a נזיר nazir for the first
part. And it says...
okay, okay let's finish reading that תוספות. Tosfos. Okay. כשישתה k'sheyishteh ואיהו
v'ihu אינו eino רוצה rotzeh לשתות lishtos ואמר נזיר nazir. הוא hu
לסלקם l'salkam מעליו me'alav שאם she'im לא יאמר yomar נזיר nazir. הוא
יביאו yaviu לו כוס אחר. acher. לכך l'kach אמר amar נזיר nazir
לסלקם l'salkam לגמרי legamrei מעליו me'alav to completely get them off his
back. Or her. אבל aval כשאינו k'she'eino שיכור shikor אין ein דרך
derech להפצירו l'haftziro when you're not drunk people aren't pressuring you to
drink wine that you have to use such a harsh word. They're
just saying, hey buddy, I just said, do you want another cup
of wine? Like okay, you know, calm down. All right,
so nobody's pressuring you because you know, you're not... position to be
taken advantage of and made fun of. It's really sad what's describing
here. Anyway, אינו דרך לאפצירה eino derech l'aftzira ולכך אומר דנזיר מכולהו.
ul'kach omer d'nazir mikulehu. So when you use the word נזיר nazir
there, why'd you have to use such a harsh word? Nobody was
giving you a hard time. So if you're going to use that
heavy word of נזיר, nazir. you really mean that you're going to
be a נזיר nazir like a full נזיר nazir. from wine, and
once you're a נזיר nazir. from wine, not just this cup or
whatever, then you're a נזיר nazir. from everything as well. Okay, so
that's thank you, that's helpful for explaining why also we have the
ruling in the first part of the משנה. mishna Again, I would
guess that if somebody said הריני נזיר hareini nazir מן הכוס הזה
that you would not be a נזיר. nazir. All right, let's take
a look. Next משנה. mishna. הריני נזיר על מנת שאהא שותה יין
ומיטמא למתים. hareini nazir al mnat she'ehei shoteh yayin umitamei lameitim.
I'll be a נזיר, nazir, I just have a few conditions. Okay,
condition number one is I still get to drink wine. All right,
condition number two is, no, actually these are probably or, not and.
Okay, or I'll be a נזיר nazir. on the condition that I
still get to be מיטמא למתים. mitamei lameitim. You know what buddy?
הרי זה נזיר. nazir You're a נזיר nazir ואסור בכולן v'assur bekulan
and you don't get any of your conditions met. You basically accepted
נזירות, nezirot, you're not allowed to do a partial נזירות, nezirot, you've
fundamentally accepted it, so therefore you remain a נזיר Nazir. from all
of those. Now, there are two ways of understanding this. I'll just
jump, anticipate the גמרא. Gemara One way is that you basically said
I'm going to accept the full נזירות nezirot but I have a
condition. Then that's an idea of like מתנה על מה שכתוב בתורה.
matneh al mah shekatuv batorah. You don't get to make conditions against
things that the תורה torah imposes. So we ignore your conditions and
we accept your basic statement, which was you accepted נזירות. nezirot Okay.
The other approach is, no, no, when you say על מנת, al
mnat, you really mean I'm a נזיר Nazir? except in regards to
wine or except in regarding to becoming טמא. tamei. Okay. You didn't
mean like I accept the whole נזירות neziros only on condition X.
No, what you really meant was not על מנת, al mnat, you
really meant חוץ. chutz. I'm a נזיר Nazir. but I still get
to drink wine. I'm a נזיר Nazir except for the issue of
מיטמא למתים. mitamei lameitim. Well, then that gets to the issue about
you accepted part of a נזירות, neziros or part of what נזירות
neziros is about. And the basic rule we had from the earlier
משנה, mishna again, it was debated but the סתם stam of the
earlier משנה Mishna, was if you say I'm a נזיר Nazir. just
from wine, not from the other stuff, you're a נזיר Nazir for
everything. When you accept part, you've accepted the whole thing, it's a
package deal. Okay. So that's the first part of the משנה. Mishna,
Now, if a person says יודע אני שיש נזירות. yodea ani sheyesh
nezirot. Look, I know there's this idea of נזירות neziros out there.
אבל איני יודע שהנזיר אסור ביין. aval eini yodea shehanazir assur beyayin.
You know what? I never realized that a נזיר Nazir was forbidden
wine. I see these guys going with long hair, I figured this
is some weird idea that you get to grow your hair long
and nobody ever told me the wine part. Okay. הרי זה אסור.
harei zeh assur. Sorry buddy, you accepted נזירות, neziros you know, ignorance
is no excuse, and you are still a נזיר. Nazir רבי שמעון
מתיר. rabbi shimon mattir.
Is this someone who's going already to a חכם chacham להיתר? leheter?
Yeah, basically, I mean no, he's not going for.
If he's going and he wants a התרה hatara and he says
אני מתחרט, ani mitcharet, that's like a different story. We'll get to
that. Okay, but this guy is not yet saying אני מתחרט. ani
mitcharet. He's asking a פסק. psak. I look, when I accepted נזירות,
neziros you know, I thought it was only about the hair and
whatever, I didn't know about the wine. Is it still a קבלת
נזירות? kabbalat nezirot? And the answer is yes, it's a קבלת נזירות.
kabbalat nezirot. Now, if you want to try to be מתחרט, mitcharet,
we can discuss that. Okay. But fundamentally, accepting נזירות neziros, with ignorance
of that fact is still a נזיר. nazir. Okay. Exactly. But רבי
שמעון rabbi shimon says it's not. So we'll have to see about
רבי שמעון. rabbi shimon. יודע אני שהנזיר אסור ביין. yodea ani shehanazir
assur beyayin. I knew a נזיר nazir. was forbidden wine. אבל סבור
הייתי שחכמים מתירין לי. aval savur hayiti shechachamim mattirin li. But I
figured, yes, I knew what a נזיר Nazir was, but I figured
that, exactly. That's very well said. Yeah, that's for everyone else. I
figured the rabbis would give me a dispensation. מפני שאיני יכול לחיות
אלא ביין. mipnei she'eini yakhol lichyot ela beyayin. You know, I'm like
a, I'm an alcoholic, right? I can't do without wine. או מפני
שאני קובר את המתים o mipnei she'ani kover et hametim or because
I'm a gravedigger. So I figured they would give me a dispensation,
it's necessary for my פרנסה. parnasa. הרי זה מותר. harei zeh muttar.
Interesting. Oh, in that case, fine, you get out of it. Like,
huh? Why is that any better than the first case? ורבי שמעון
אוסר. v'rabbi shimon osser. And רבי שמעון rabbi shimon forbids. So they
flip their positions. In the case where you said I didn't realize
I was אסור assur with wine, the חכמים Chachamim say it's forbidden
and רבי שמעון rabbi shimon says you're not a נזיר. nazir In
the case where you say I knew it was forbidden but I
figured I'd get a dispensation, then they flip the positions, and the
חכמים Chachamim say it's מותר muttar and רבי שמעון rabbi shimon says
it's אסור. assur. Yes.
When the חכמים Chachamim say you can be a נזיר nazir, and
not have that, no, no.
When it says מותר, muttar, it means you're not a נזיר. nazir
Right, right. You don't get a partial נזירות neziros except שמשון. shimshon.
It means when it's מותר, muttar, it means you don't become a
נזיר. nazir Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara. says like this.
וליפלוג נמי רבי שמעון ברישא. v'liflog nami rabbi shimon bereisha. So why
doesn't רבי שמעון, rabbi shimon, so before we get to the reversal
of positions in the second and third case, we're going to look
at the first case. The first case is you say I'm a
נזיר על מנת nazir al mnat that I get to still drink
wine. Okay. And that was unanimous, you're not a נזיר. nazir. I
mean seriously, you are a נזיר. nazir, You are a נזיר, nazir,
right? When you say על מנת. al mnat. So but when you
say, when you say I didn't realize wine was included, רבי שמעון,
rabbi shimon, you know, that's where רבי שמעון rabbi shimon said you're
not a נזיר. nazir. So if רבי שמעון rabbi shimon says you're
not a נזיר nazir when you said I didn't think wine was
included, why doesn't he say you're not a נזיר nazir when you
say על מנת al mnat that I'm still allowed to drink wine?
Right, maybe it would be clear if I put, let me put
all three cases. I know, I know, I just want to put
all three cases on the משנה Mishna. deal. Okay. Number one was
על מנת שאשתה יין, Al m'nas she'eshteh yayin, okay, and that was
everybody, everybody says in that case you're a נזיר. nazir, Number two
was, right, what was the phrase that he used?
איני יודע.
Eni yodea.
איני יודע שנזיר אסור ביין,
Eni yodea she-nazir
assur beyayin, and there you have חכמים Hachamim. saying אסור assur and
רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon saying מותר, mutar, okay, אינו נזיר, eno nazir,
right, which means אינו נזיר.
eno nazir.
Okay, and then number three was סבור הייתי, savur hayiti, yeah, שחכמים
מתירים לי.
she-chachamim matirim
li. סבור הייתי שחכמים מתירים,
savur hayiti she-chachamim
matirim, and here you get מותר mutar and רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon
says אסור. assur. Very confusing, right? So one question is why do
they reverse themselves here? Okay, and the other question is why is
there no debate when you say על מנת שאשתה יין? Al m'nas
she'eshteh yayin? Why does everybody assume you're a נזיר? nazir Let רבי
שמעון, Rebbe Shimon, who says when you thought it wasn't included you're
מותר, mutar, say when you explicitly stipulate that it shouldn't be included
you're מותר. mutar. Okay, so let's take a look. וליפלוג נמי רבי
שמעון ברישא? V'liflog nami Rebbe Shimon b'reisha? אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי,
Amar Rebbe Yehoshua ben Levi, חולק היה רבי שמעון אף ארישא. Cholok
hayah Rebbe Shimon af areisha. Yeah, you're right, he debates the first
case, he just didn't get around to saying it. All right, רזינא
אמר, Razina amar, רזינא Razina says ברישא לא פליג רבי שמעון. B'reisha
lo palig Rebbe Shimon. No, no, no, he agrees in the first
case you're a נזיר. nazir מאי טעמא? Mai taama? What's the reason?
משום דהוי ליה מתנה על מה שכתוב בתורה וכל המתנה על מה
שכתוב בתורה תנאו בטל, Mishum d'havei leh matneh al mah she-kasuv ba-Torah
v'chol hamatneh al mah she-kasuv ba-Torah tnao batel, because you're stipulating against
what's in the Torah, and therefore any stipulation against the Torah you
throw out the stipulation. You can't make a condition about the status
in the Torah. You're saying I fully accept the נזירות neziros but
here's my condition. Okay, you don't get to make conditions and to
change what the rules of the game are. Okay, but in this
case, right, you were not saying I fully accept the נזירות neziros.
and I know all pieces of it. You actually in your mind
were only accepting a נזירות neziros that was different from the real
נזירות neziros, of the Torah. Here you understood the נזירות neziros of
the Torah and you tried to somehow change the rules, then we
ignore your stipulation because you fundamentally accepted the נזירות neziros as opposed
to this case you didn't fundamentally accept the full נזירות, neziros at
least that's what רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon would say. You accepted a
נזירות neziros that was a different type of, that was something different.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara. says
if you take a look תוספות Tosfos spells this out nicely. האי
על מנת, Hai al m'nas, I'm sorry, no, let's read another line
in the גמרא. Gemara Okay, רבי יהושע בן לוי אמר לך, Rebbe
Yehoshua ben Levi amar lach, and רבי יהושע בן לוי Rebbe Yehoshua
ben Levi that said, no,
רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon debates the first case as well. האי על
מנת כחוץ דמי. Hai al m'nas k'chutz dami. No, על מנת al
m'nas is like saying חוץ, chutz, right, it's like saying I'm a
נזיר nazir from wine and, you know, my נזירות neziros. includes wine
and doesn't include becoming טמא. tamei. All right, so it's exactly the
same as the, as this case. You try to accept a partial
נזירות. neziros. In this case it was partial, and רבי שמעון Rebbe
Shimon says it's not binding. So here too, do you say it's
whole נזירות neziros? with a condition? If so, רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon
would agree it doesn't work, you're a נזיר. nazir If you say
it's partial נזירות, neziros, then that just gets back to the second
debate where רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon says it's מותר. mutar. Now, what
is the reason for the second debate? So the reason for the
second debate is, I will remind you that when somebody just says
a simpler case: הריני נזיר מן היין, Hareini nazir min hayayin, or
even if you say רק מן היין, rak min hayayin, right, forget
the חוץ, chutz, הריני נזיר רק מן היין. Hareini nazir rak min
hayayin. So the חכמים Hachamim said earlier, once you accept נזירות neziros,
for part you're a נזיר nazir for the whole thing. Guess who
the one who disagreed was? רבי שמעון. Rebbe Shimon. רבי שמעון Rebbe
Shimon said until you accept נזירות neziros, from everything. Okay, so there's
a basic debate: can you become a נזיר nazir. by accepting one
piece of it and the rest gets schlepped along, or do you
have to accept the whole thing? That's what's going on in this
second case. When you said I thought that נזירות nezirus, didn't apply
to wine, you're basically saying in my, I was imagining, like if
we think about נזירות nezirus as like, right, this three-part thing,
יין, yayin,
תגלחת, tiglachas, and מתים, meisim, in your mind, you were not accepting
full נזירות. nezirus You were accepting, you were accepting that, that was
your concept of נזירות. nezirus, Well, what's the story if you accept
a piece of the נזירות? nezirus. So the חכמים Hachamim say you
accepted a piece, you accepted the whole thing. רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon
says you accepted a piece, you didn't accept anything. That's, that's why
he says it's מותר. mutar. In the first case, there's two ways
of looking at it. Either you could look at it as you've
accepted the whole נזירות, nezirus, but you say yeah, I accept upon
myself this whole נזירות, nezirus. but I've got some conditions. You know,
I have some conditions on it. Okay, and so you know what
we say? You've accepted the whole נזירות, nezirus you don't get to
make conditions, so then you're a נזיר nazir even according to רבי
שמעון. Rebbe Shimon. But if you say על מנת al m'nas is
like חוץ, chutz, I'm not saying the whole thing with conditions, I'm
saying I'm only accepting part of it. Then that just gets back
to the second debate. So the question is... The question is whether
would רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon agree,
say his position here as well, depends. If you say על מנת
al m'nas means חוץ, chutz, it's a partial נזירות, nezirus, then it
is the same debate. If you say על מנת al m'nas means
I accept the whole thing but I've got some conditions, then it's
a different debate and then even רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would agree.
Okay, take a look at תוספות. Tosafos. He spells this out. "האי
על מנת כחוץ דמי", Hai al m'nas k'chutz dami, "כי הוא אמר
הריני נזיר מכל מילי חוץ מן היין דלא הוי נזיר לרבי שמעון
דבעינן עד שידור מכולם". ki hu amar hareni nazir mikol mili chutz
min hayayin d'lo havei nazir l'Rabbi Shimon d'ba'inan ad sheyidor mikulam. Okay.
So because then you're basically saying it's a partial נזירות nezirus and
then it's not, as opposed to it's a full
נזירות nezirus,
without actually, I'm sorry, what I also want to read is the
first line of the previous תוספות. Tosafos. "דהוי מתנה על מה שכתוב
בתורה דכשאמר הריני נזיר חל עליו נזירות לכל מילי". D'havei masneh al
mah shekatuv baTorah d'k'sh'amar hareni nazir chal alav nezirus l'chol mili. Then
you're accepting the full package. "וכי אמר על מנת מטיל תנאי על
מה שכתוב בתורה ובטל התנאי". v'ki amar al m'nas matil tnai al
mah shekatuv baTorah u'vatel hatnai. Then you're trying to make conditions and
we reject your conditions. Okay.
So if it's a partial נזירות, nezirus that's case two and that's
the debate of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and the חכמים. Hachamim If
it's על מנת, al m'nas, well, how do you read על מנת?
al m'nas? If you read על מנת al m'nas as partial, it's
the same debate. If you read על מנת al m'nas as full
with a condition, then even רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would agree that
you don't get to make conditions. Okay, let's take a look now
at the גמרא.
Gemara It's like, you know, to actually sort of have this work
is to take a
נדר neder instead of saying נזיר. nazir Exactly. Okay, but then you
don't have the קרבנות, korbanot, you have a whole different thing. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
"תניא כוותיה דרבינא", Tanya k'vasei d'Ravina, we
taught like רבינא. Ravina. "אמר הריני נזיר על מנת שאהא שותה יין
ומטמא למתים הרי זה נזיר ואסור
בכולם מפני שהוא מתנה על מה שכתוב בתורה וכל המתנה על מה
שכתוב בתורה תנאו בטל". Amar hareni nazir al m'nas she'ehei shoteh yayin
u'mitameh l'mesim harei zeh nazir v'asur b'kulam mipnei shehu masneh al mah
shekatuv baTorah v'chol hamasneh al mah shekatuv baTorah tna'o batel. Okay, so
basically that says that it's based on מתנה על מה שכתוב בתורה.
masneh al mah shekatuv baTorah. It's not because it's חוץ, chutz, it's
not because it's partial, it's the full thing with a condition and
we throw out your condition. And therefore presumably רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
would concede in that case that you are a full נזיר. nazir
Now we get to comparing, so that was comparing case one and
case two. Now we get to comparing case two and case three.
Why do they reverse themselves? This case we said was partial and
that's the debate, the חכמים Hachamim say partial is full and רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says partial is nothing. How about this case when
we said I thought the חכמים Chachamim, would allow it to me?
Okay, now that's not exactly the same as partial because again you
know that you're forbidden, you just thought you'd get a dispensation. So
we understand why it's not the exact same as partial but we
still want to understand why their positions reversed. Okay, so let's take
a look. "יודע אני שנזירות אסורה". Yodea ani she'nezirus asurah. Yeah, yeah,
I knew the full thing, I just thought I'd get a dispensation.
So the גמרא Gemara says "ואמרת רישא אסור ורבי שמעון מתיר". V'amarta
reisha asur v'Rabbi Shimon matir. One minute,
at the end of the day you thought it would be partial.
Whether because of a dispensation this time because you thought of a
dispensation. So shouldn't that be the same debate? That the חכמים Chachamim
say forbidden, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it's permissible. "אימא נמי הרי
זה אסור ורבי שמעון מתיר". Eima nami harei zeh asur v'Rabbi Shimon
matir. Okay, you know what? Fine. Reverse, reverse the end of the
משנה, Mishnah get it all be the same, which is so boring.
I mean, you know, it's hard to imagine that the person who
wrote a משנה, Mishnah if it was literally the same debate, you
know, just reversed the names here at the end. But the first
answer is the easiest one. Fine, it's the same thing, reverse the
names, have them all say the same thing.
I
know, it's נדרים nedarim and נזיר Nazir, different language. Okay, now we'll
get to the more interesting answers. "איבעית אימא לעולם לא תיפוך". Iba'is
eima l'olam lo sipoach. See there you go, so it didn't have
the word "איפוך". ipoach. Don't reverse the names. "התם רישא כגון דנזר
מחדא". Hasam reisha k'gon d'nazar michada. In the first case, meaning now
what I'm having up here as number two, okay, you were a
נזיר Nazir. only a partial נזיר, Nazir you only tried to accept
one of the aspects of נזירות. nezirus. "לרבנן דאמרי אפילו לא נזר
אלא מאחת מהן הוי נזיר ואסור". L'rabbanan d'amri afilu lo nazar ela
m'achas mehen havei nazir v'asur.
And that's the debate of the Rabbis and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
because that's exactly the debate we had in an earlier משנה. Mishnah.
The Rabbis say if you try to become a נזיר Nazir. just
from one thing, like from the wine part, you get the, you're
a נזיר Nazir. from the whole, you try to do partial you
get the whole. "ורבי שמעון דאמר עד שידור מכולן מותר". v'Rabbi Shimon
d'amar ad sheyidor mikulan mutar. But רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says
no, unless you accept the full, the full package, if you try,
then it's nothing, a partial package is nothing. That's this debate. It
was a partial, you did a partial package because you didn't think
wine was included and hey, and Michael I should say by the
way, here your words were full נזירות, nezirus you just told me
what you were thinking and that's still relevant. Somehow we say because
you weren't thinking that wine was included, what you were really doing
was accepting partial נזירות. nezirus. Right? So that's important, like what do
you mean? I don't care you didn't say it, it doesn't matter,
somehow we acknowledge that this was partial נזירות nezirus, and that's the
old debate, partial נזירות, nezirus, חכמים Chachamim, say it's everything and רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it's nothing. That explains number two, good, that
we had. Now let's go on to number three. Okay.
"סיפא דנזר
מכולהו". Seifa d'nazar mikulhu. The סיפא seifa is no, no, no, I
understood what נזירות nezirus. was, I was accepting to be a full
נזיר. Nazir "ואיתשיל מחדא". v'itshil michada.
But what I'm doing is... Is when I said I thought חכמים
מתירין לי, Chachamim matirin li, Michael, here what we're explaining it is,
you really are going and asking for a היתר. heter. Okay, so
in the other case, in the סיפא seifa we're saying, yeah, I
accepted the full נזירות, but now I am actually coming and saying
I need a היתר heter because I've because I have a job
as a gravedigger. Okay, so לרבנן דאמרי אפילו נזר על אחת מהן
הוי נזיר, lerabanan deamri afilu nazar al achas meihen havi nazir, so
the same way the rabbis say when you accepted a נזירות from
one thing, wine, you become a full נזיר, Nazir, so you know
what? כי מיתשיל מחדא מינייהו אישתרי. ki mitshil michada mineihu ishtari. Let's
say you have a reason to find a היתר heter for, you
have חרטה charata for the wine part of the נדר, neder. okay,
of the נזירות. Does that satisfy as being a חרטה charata and
can we do a היתר heter for your נדר neder. even if
you weren't מתחרט mitcharet for all of it, you only מתחרט mitcharet
for part of it? You understand the question? We had this back
in נדרים. nedarim I basically say that a נדר neder that I'm
going to say all red meat is אסור assur to me. And
then I realize, ah, I wasn't thinking about Shabbos. I want to
still be able to have my cholent on Shabbos, okay? So I
go for a היתר heter for the חכם chacham and he says,
you're right, that was a good חרטה, charata, you hadn't been thinking
about that. Okay, so now we're going to be מתיר matir your
נדר. neder So what's the end result? Can I eat red meat
all the time or can I just eat red meat on Shabbos?
Right, so that's the question of נדר שהותר מקצתו הותר כולו, neder
she-hutar mikzato hutar kulo, right? Do you need to undo have a
חרטה charata on the totality or even on part? So what the
גמרא Gemara is here saying is that by נזיר, Nazir that debate
would be the mirror image of how do you become a נזיר.
Nazir So if by becoming a נזיר Nazir, for just the wine,
I become a נזיר Nazir, for the whole thing, position of the
חכמים, chachamim right, you do wine you do the whole thing, then
it also works the same in reverse. When I regret just the
wine, that constitutes a חרטה charata and therefore I'm freed from the
whole part. According to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, he says no, you
have to accept the whole נזירות and you have to be מתחרט
mitcharet on the whole נזירות. So in this case, this case is
you're מתחרט mitcharet or you're asking for maybe, you know, you're asking
for a היתר heter through the process of התרה, hatara, okay? And
therefore that's why their positions reverse. You're just מתחרט mitcharet from the
from the coming טמא, tamei, fine, the חכמים say part equals all.
That's a חרטה charata we're going to be מתיר matir your נדר.
neder And רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says, I'm sorry, you need to
be מתחרט mitcharet or you need to have
a, you know, a
היתר heter on
the whole thing.
It's all one big package deal. Okay, now, משום הכי קתני mishum
hachi katani and that explains רבי שמעון אוסר Rabbi Shimon oseir perfect,
that exactly explains why it's a mirror image. That's a very elegant
explanation. Although I do want to point out to you that
it makes if you think about it for a minute, it doesn't
make sense in terms of the end result. It makes sense in
terms of the process. Because if I say when I'm a נזיר,
Nazir. if I accept a part נזירות, I get the whole thing,
that means that just being a נזיר Nazir, from the wine can
make me a נזיר Nazir? on everything, right? So then why don't
we say, so then even if I got a התרה hatara from
the טומאת tumas from being מטמא למתים, mitamei le-meisim, I'm still left
with being a נזיר nazir from wine. And being a נזיר nazir?
from wine makes me a נזיר nazir. from everything, right? So in
a sense, it's like it actually shouldn't be the mirror image, it
should be the exact same because okay, even if you take away
that piece, as long as you're still holding onto a piece of
it for the חכמים, right, that should, you know, that should still
make you a נזיר. nazir So the answer point is that we're
not looking at the end result. We're looking at the process. The
process of קבלת נזירות kabalas nezirus is a process that relates even
to a piece of what a נזיר nazir. is and the process
of התרה hatara also can relate to just a piece of what
it is. Whereas רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says no, the process, the
act of קבלה kabala has to relate to the whole thing and
the act of התרה hatara also has to relate to the whole
thing. So we're not looking at what sort is the status, you
know, the end of sort of you know like restrictions that apply
to you. We're talking about what is the act. The act of
קבלה kabala is on part and the act of התרה hatara is
on part or the act of קבלה kabala is on all and
the act of התרה hatara is on all. Okay, yes.
One would assume then if the נזיר nazir. said to רבי שמעון,
Rabbi Shimon, instead of saying I can't accept the part about טומאה
tuma because I'm a gravedigger, but said I realized טומאה tuma came
as part of it, I have to be released my entire
נזירות, right, see, so that's like an interesting question which I don't
really have and haven't like figured out because like
if I'm going for a התרה, hatara, I'm saying look, exactly that,
I'm saying like look, if I had, you know, realized that this
whole thing was a package deal and was all or nothing and
part of this package included that I can't be מטמא למתים, mitamei
le-meisim, I never would have accepted the
package. So open... the whole thing because it comes as a package
deal, right? So I don't understand, you're completely correct and I don't
understand like you know what is the case here where שמעון Shimon
says oh no no no you're only focusing on part. Like I
guess it would be a scenario I imagine again I I don't
know but I imagine the difference is is like if I'm saying
what I just said look if it's all or nothing then I
didn't want to be a נזיר nazir. because I can't accept all
of it so I wouldn't have wanted. Okay so ultimately you're מתחרט
mischaret on the whole thing. But if I said no no no
I still am okay with the rest of it I just want
you to get me out of this part I'm only מתחרט mischaret
on this part so then I can't help you like you know
so it might just be a question of how you're actually framing
it. Are you framing it knowing this I'm מתחרט mischaret on everything
fine then you're מתחרט mischaret on everything but if you say no
I'm not מתחרט mischaret on that I'm only מתחרט mischaret on that
so buddy you know like learn how to play the game. But
okay that seems like that's the difference but I agree with you
it is strange because bottom line it is a package deal. Okay
so the גמרא Gemara says like this okay so that was a
nice way of explaining the mirror image. Now it says like this
איבעית אימא ibeis eima here's a third answer בנדרי אונסין benidrei onsin
קמיפלגי kamifalgi
it's about an אונס נדר. ones neder. Now there are ארבע נדרים
arba nedarim that a נדר neder is not binding okay and let's
see what that is ובפלוגתא דשמואל ורב אסי ubiplugta deShmuel verav Assi
and it's a debate of שמואל Shmuel and רב אסי. Rav Assi.
דתנן detnan we taught in a משנה Mishnah ארבע נדרים התירו חכמים
arba nedarim hatiru chachamim there are four נדרים that the חכמים permitted.
What are they? נדרי זירוזין nidrei ziruzin
a נדר neder of like encouragement which basically is like you know
you're haggling over the price on something and one says a נדר
neder if I go any lower than then then twenty a נדר
neder if I go any higher than ten so nobody really means
a נדר neder it's just a way of haggling. נדרי הבאי nidrei
havai sort of נדרים of like nonsense which are basically like oh
a נדר neder like I saw a snake as big as a
house or something like that again doesn't not really serious. נדרי שגגות
nidrei shegagot a נדר neder of of unintentional which doesn't mean you
violated it unintentionally it more means you stipulated a condition and you
didn't realize that the condition had actually been met. So the actual
you thought that you were that the נדר neder was not taking
effect not you thought you weren't violating it you thought it wasn't
taking effect
and it really was okay and so none of that is relevant
for us. נדרי אונסין. nidrei onsin. Now what's the נדרי אונסין? nidrei
onsin? נדרי אונסין nidrei onsin is a case where I say like
a נדר my stuff will be forbidden to you if you don't
come to my birthday party and then you didn't come to my
birthday party but the reason was was because you know there was
like a three hour right a three hour traffic jam or whatever.
So the point is oh well I didn't mean that I meant
that if you like willingly don't come to my birthday party you're
an אונס ones I didn't mean that that would be a condition
in which I would want the נדר to take effect. How is
it relevant here? Some way the גמרא Gemara thinks that this is
something like a נדרי אונסין nidrei onsin because it's sort of like
the traffic jam it's sort of like oh you know like I
wouldn't you know I I have a special case I've gotta I've
gotta be a grave digger you know and I therefore I wouldn't
have in that case like I would've thought that I wouldn't have
wanted my נדר to take effect if I realized it would have
gotten in the way of the things that I need to do
like go ahead and be a grave digger or my נזירות. So
somehow I don't know don't push me too much on that somehow
they think of that as a type of a נדרי אונסין nidrei
onsin okay. But let's see what how what the relevant part of
the debate is. ואמר רב יהודה אמר רב אסי ve'amar Rav Yehuda
amar Rav Assi ארבע נדרים הללו צריכים שאלה לחכמים arba nedarim halalu
tzrichim she'eila lachachamim these four נדרים you even though it says that
they're מותר muttar you need to go and do an act of
התרת נדרים hataras nedarim and that's דרבנן derabbanan so we shouldn't treat
it too lightly okay because because
it really means you didn't have basic דעת da'as but nevertheless דרבנן
derabbanan we make you go through this process. כי אמריתה קמי דשמואל
ki amritah kamei deShmuel when that was said over in front of
שמואל Shmuel אמר לי amar li he said תנא תני התירו חכמים
tanna tani hatiru chachamim the language in the משנה Mishnah is the
rabbis released you from it which means it's not binding at all.
ואת אמרת צריכים שאלה לחכמים ve'at amrat tzrichim she'eila lachachamim and you
say you need to go through some process you don't need to
go through any process. So רבנן סברי כשמואל ורבי שמעון סבר כרבי
אסי. rabbanan savri keShmuel veRabbi Shimon savar keRabbi Assi. So what it's
saying is is that this I don't I'll say in a minute
another word about why we're calling it נדרי אונסין nidrei onsin but
this is a type of a thing that shouldn't be binding. You
didn't realize that you thought it wasn't going to you know you
would have never have accepted it if you had known that you
wouldn't be able to continue as a grave digger. To the first
part? Yeah yeah but fine that's just you סתם stipulated but here
deep down you fundamentally never would have accepted it it would have
compromised your job as a
grave digger. Okay so in that case right so fine it's not
binding on you at all what's the story? The question is so
that's why it's מותר. muttar. When שמעון Shimon says אסור assur he
doesn't mean it's אסור assur this is what I said back to
Michael earlier. It's אסור assur now. Right now it's binding. You want
to go ask התרה hatarah do a חרטה charata be my guest
of course you could do a חרטה charata in this situation. When
we say אסור assur it doesn't mean you can't do a חרטה
charata it just means that right now it's binding. Okay and then
you have to if you want to undo it you'll have to
undo it. Okay so they're not really disagreeing that this is a
basis for undoing they're saying whether that makes it not binding from
the get-go okay that's the way the גמרא Gemara explains. Now תוספות
Tosafot says a word About because this doesn't really at all fit
the נדרי אונסים Nidrei Onesim category. So תוספות Tosafot says it doesn't
really mean נדרי אונסים. Nidrei Onesim. If you take a look at
תוספות, Tosafot, middle of נדרי הבאי, Nidrei Havai, תוספות Tosafot says the
following.
אי נמי, Ee nami, it's a line that starts with the word
נמי, nami, it's like three, six, seven lines before the תוספות Tosafot
of הריני, line starts with the word נמי. nami. He says אי
נמי מאי דאייתי להא דין זה
היכא דהכא דאין פיו ולבו שווין. Ee nami mai d'aytei l'ha din
zeh heicha d'hacha d'ein piv v'libo shavin. It's really not a problem
of נדרי אונסים, Nidrei Onesim, it's really a problem, here you go,
of אין פיו ולבו שווין, ein piv v'libo shavin, that what you're
saying is not what you're intending. דפליגי בההיא התם אמוראי אי בעי
שאלה מדרבנן והכא נמי פליגי הכי. D'peligi b'hahi hatam Amorai ee ba'ei
sheilah mi'derabbanan v'hacha nami peligi hachi. So it's really the same question
when it's not פיו ולבו שווין. piv v'libo shavin. You said הריני
נזיר, nazir. but then you tell us, I gotta tell you, I
was thinking something completely different. I didn't know what those words meant,
etc., etc. So do we say, fine, don't worry about it, you're
done? Or do we say, okay, that's fine, let's just go through
a process of התרה. hattarah. מותר לך מותר לך מותר לך. Mutar
lach, mutar lach, mutar lach. Okay? And the reason for that is
that even though fundamentally it's not binding, you know, if we just
tell you don't worry about it, it'll too much trivialize it. You
know, I think I told you this, like my son came back
from camp and he said, and he said, I took this, I
took this vow, etc., etc. I said, so I say wait, what
did you say? etc., etc. I said, don't worry, whatever, it's not
binding. He said, he says, no, no, no, you gotta do something.
So I said, so I said, okay, מותר לך מותר לך מותר
לך. Mutar lach, mutar lach, mutar lach. He says, ah, feel so
much better. So okay, anyway, so anyway, so here I don't know
if we're doing it for the guy's psychology or we're doing it
to protect, you know, in general that people don't treat it lightly.
But if it's not פיו ולבו שווין, piv v'libo shavin, there's a
debate of do you have to go through a process of התרת
נדרים? hattarat nedarim? So תוספות Tosafot says it's not really נדרי אונסים,
Nidrei Onesim, it's really אין פיו ולבו שווין. ein piv v'libo shavin.
You say you're נזיר, nazir, but סבור הייתי, savur hayiti, like I
didn't think it was going to require me not to be able
to go into a graveyard, I would never have accepted it under
those circumstances, I can't live like that. So then one position is
fine, it's not binding, goodbye, and the other by saying אסור assur
doesn't really mean אסור, assur, it's אין פיו ולבו שווין, ein piv
v'libo shavin, but it means it's אסור assur until you go through
a process. Okay? So that's the other explanation completely unrelated. So one
explanation is that this is a mirror image because the process of
התרה hattarah and this is talking with התרה, hattarah, not automatically. This
is through התרה, hattarah, and the process of התרה hattarah has to
be the reverse, you know, or, you know, or parallels or whatever,
the process of קבלה kabbalah and that's why their positions are mirror
image. And the other explanations are really explanations about, about like whether
you have to, you know, go through a process of התרה hattarah
even, even when it is not binding. All right, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. הריני נזיר, nazir.
next משנה. Mishnah הריני נזיר ועליי לגלח, Hareini Nazir v'alai l'gale'ach, נזיר.
nazir I am a נזיר nazir. and I accept upon myself the
responsibility also to shave another נזיר. Now, I don't know if that
literally means taking out your shaver and your scissors, what it more
means as we're going to see is bringing the קרבנות korbanot for
him. I accept upon myself the responsibility to bring the קרבנות korbanot
for another נזיר. Okay? Very generous of you. ושמע חבירו ואמר ואני
ועליי לגלח נזיר. V'shama chaveiro v'amar v'ani v'alai l'gale'ach Nazir.
And a friend says what a great idea, I'll also be another
נזיר and I'll also accept responsibility of shaving another נזיר, of taking
their קרבנות. korbanot. אם היו פקחין מגלחין זה את זה. Im hayu
pikchin, megalechin zeh et zeh. If they're smart,
then what they do is, then rather than each one of them
having to A, do two sets of קרבנות, korbanot, your own and
the one you're doing for somebody else, and then find the other
guy who needs you to bring their קרבנות, korbanot, just get together
with this other person and each one of you only has to
bring one set of קרבנות korbanot and you bring each other's קרבנות
korbanot and you don't have to find the guy and you don't
have to bring two sets, you just bring for one another. Okay?
ואם לאו מגלחין נזירים אחרים. V'im lav, megalechin nezirim acherim. If they
can't find somebody else, then they have to go around and look
for other, for other נזירים. nezirim. Okay? איבעיא להו. Iba'ya lehu. They
raise the question. שמע חבירו ואמר ואני, Shama chaveiro v'amar v'ani, when
the friend heard and said, "and me," מהו? mahu? what is, if
he didn't say "me and I'll accept shave another נזיר"? You just
said, "I'm נזיר and I'm going to shave a נזיר, take the
קרבנות korbanot of another נזיר," and I said "me too." So does
the "me too" mean for both parts of it, or does it
just mean for part of it? Okay? Because the משנה Mishnah, said
I said "me too and I'll shave another נזיר." אכולי דיבורא משמע,
A'kulei dibura mashma, is
it going on everything? או דלמא פלגא דדיבורא משמע, O dilma palga
d'dibura mashma, only on half of it? Okay? With if you just
said "me too" without "and I'll shave." אם תימצי לומר פלגא דדיבורא
משמע, Im timtzi lomar palga d'dibura mashma, and if it only goes
on half of your two-part statement, which half? ארישא, A'reisha, the first
part where you say "I'll be a נזיר," או אסיפא, o a'seifa,
or the end part where you said you'll do the קרבנות korbanot
for another נזיר? Okay, good question. תא שמע, Ta shema, come and
hear. If our משנה Mishnah, said ואני ועליי לגלח נזיר, v'ani v'alai
l'gale'ach Nazir,
"and me and I'll also shave another," אם היו פקחין מגלחין זה
את זה, im hayu pikchin, megalechin zeh et zeh, if they're smart
they'll do each other's. Okay. מדקתני ואני ועליי, Mi'de'katani v'ani v'alai, since
you had to say both things in the משנה Mishnah, to create
the scenario, you had to say "me and I'll shave," שמע מינה
ואני אפלגא דדיבורא. shma mina v'ani a'palga d'dibura.
If you just said "and me," it wouldn't have gotten you into
that situation, it would have only been a partial acceptance. אמרי, Amrei,
and you also say, אין אפלגא דדיבורא משמע. in, a'palga d'dibura mashma.
Fine, I accept that. ואני va'ani would have just been for would
not covered the whole piece. You needed the other half of your
statement.
But מדקאמר רישא או סיפא, mideka'amar reisha o seifa, so but would
the ואני va'ani itself have been the first part of the statement
being a נזיר or the second part shaving another נזיר? That's also
obvious, right? The גמרא Gemara says מנא mina you can learn it
out from that case itself מדקאמר ועלי לגלח, mideka'amar va'alai legaleach, since
A, you needed ועלי לגלח, va'alai legaleach, it shows you ואני va'ani
doesn't do the whole job by itself. And since ועלי לגלח va'alai
legaleach takes part of the second part of the sentence, clearly the
ואני va'ani took part of the first part of the sentence. שמע
מינה ואני, shma mina va'ani, I'm sorry, שמע מינה ואני על תחילת
דיבורא משמע. shma mina va'ani al techilat dibura mashma. That seems like
a very obvious, you know, read of the משנה, Mishnah right? You
had to say two parts. So ואני, va'ani, if I asked you
after having read the משנה, Mishnah if you just said ואני, va'ani,
what would that have meant? Say well it sounds like from the
משנה, Mishnah. if you had just said אני, ani, it means I'll
be a נזיר. And therefore you have to add ועלי לגלח va'alai
legaleach in order to add the second part. Okay, that's very reasonable.
אמר ליה רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע לרבא, Amar lei Rav Huna
breih de'Rav Yehoshua le'Rava, Rav Huna son of Rav Huna said to
Rava, of Rav Yehoshua said to Rava, ממאי דהכי? mimai dehachi? Who
said that that's the way it is? לעולם אימא לך אל סיפא
והוא הדין לכוליה דיבורא. le'olam eima lach al seifa vehu hadin le'chulei
dibura. If you just said ואני, va'ani, you would have been everything,
a נזיר and had this extra responsibility. ואי משום דעלי, ve'i mishum
de'alai, and if about the fact that the משנה Mishnah says that
you said ועלי לגלח, va'alai legaleach, מאי קאמר? mai ka'amar? What is
he saying? ועלי בהא מילתא. va'alai be'ha milta. Yeah, and it'll be
on me this thing,
meaning basically not saying anything, you're just being repetitive or you know,
you're just being clarifying. Yeah, fine. ואני va'ani would have been enough.
Okay, the משנה Mishnah. is just added those extra words but you
really wouldn't technologically need them—technically need them. Okay. ואי לא תימא הכי,
ve'i lo teima hachi, if you don't say that, דקתני סיפא, de'katani
seifa, we have a coming up משנה. Mishnah הרי עלי לגלח חצי
נזיר. Harei alai legaleach chatzi nazir. I will shave half of a
נזיר. Okay, which means which means I'll do half the
קרבנות. korbanot. ושמע חבירו ואמר ואני לגלח חצי נזיר. v'shama chaveiro v'amar
va'ani legaleach chatzi nazir. And another friend says and I also will
do
the
same. Okay. מי איכא תרתי מילי?
mi ika
tarti mili? Why are there two things? Oh right, right, because I'm
sorry, the point here is, yeah, that's one. Forget the חצי, chatzi,
that's a distraction. The point is you didn't say I'm a נזיר.
In the next משנה Mishnah. all you said was I will be
מגלח חצי נזיר. megaleach chatzi nazir. You're only talking about your responsibility
to bring the other guy's קרבנות. korbanot. There's no you being a
נזיר. That's the case in the next משנה. Mishnah ואי לא תימא
הכי דקתני סיפא הרי עלי לגלח חצי נזיר. ve'i lo teima hachi
de'katani seifa harei alai legaleach chatzi nazir. All you're doing is accepting,
you know, take the קרבנות korbanot of another נזיר. ושמע חבירו ואמר
ואני עלי לגלח חצי נזיר. v'shama chaveiro v'amar va'ani alai legaleach chatzi
nazir. Me too, I'll also do חצי נזיר. chatzi nazir. So there
there's only one thing you said. מי איכא תרתי מילי? mi ika
tarti mili? You didn't, you only said one thing. You didn't say
you're a נזיר, you just said your responsibility for the other נזיר.
So and you could have just said ואני. va'ani. So the next
משנה Mishnah there was no question halachically it could have been framed
that all the second guy said was ואני va'ani and nevertheless it
has him make a full sentence. ואני ועלי לגלח. va'ani va'alai legaleach.
אלא מאי קאמר? ella mai ka'amar? עלי בהא מילתא. alai be'ha milta.
He means and me and then he's spelling out what he means
by the and me. הכי נמי כי קאמר עלי בהא מילתא. hachi
nami ki ka'amar alai be'ha milta. Here too he's spelling it out
to basically saying don't get hung up, don't overly halachically read, technically
read the phrase in the משנה. It's just giving you an example
of what the guy is saying. He's saying a full complete clear
sentence. But you know what? Halachically, even if you just say ואני
va'ani it means everything and that's clear because in the next משנה
there was only one thing it could have meant and it still
had him say a full sentence. Yes.
So there's a bit of a, the first one you say ואני
ועלי לגלח. va'ani va'alai legaleach.
Right, so that could have made it everything. ואני עלי לגלח. va'ani
alai legaleach. So right. Yeah, absolutely. So I don't know, I noticed
that too and you know also you have to see sometimes like
there might be some manuscript variants. But yes, the גמרא Gemara could
have certainly made that difference. If you don't have the ו vav
then yes, it's one sentence. With the ו vav then so absolutely.
So let's see how the גמרא responds. Okay, so yeah.
You can also say that ואני va'ani means nothing.
No, because that we have the very first משנה that if a
נזיר is עובר לפניך over lefaneicha and you say ואני va'ani or
something like that, you hear somebody saying הריני נזיר and you say
ואני, va'ani, you're a נזיר. That clearly we know from other משניות.
Mishnayot. Okay, so the גמרא says like this. אמר ליה
רבא הכי השתא? Amar lei Rava hachi hashta? What type of proof
is that?
אי אמרת... ei amrat... If in the first case of the משנה
*Mishnah*, אני *ani* wasn't enough and you needed a second clause, so
therefore סיפא לא צריכה *seifa lo tzricha* in the end, you didn't
need a second clause. That I could have explained. תני סיפא דלא
צריכה *Tani seifa d'lo tzricha* in the end you had a second
clause which was superfluous משום רישא דצריכה *mishum reisha d'tzricha* because in
the first case of the משנה *Mishnah*, our case it wasn't superfluous,
you needed the second clause. So that I can explain why it
has that full sentence. I agree the second משנה *Mishnah*, it was...
it was superfluous. But I don't want both משניות *Mishnayot* to be
superfluous. I can accept it being superfluous in the second if it
was necessary in the first. אלא אי אמרת רישא לא צריכה *Ella
ei amarta reisha lo tzricha*, but if it was superfluous in the
רישא *reisha* and סיפא לא צריכה *seifa lo tzricha* and it was
superfluous in the סיפא *seifa*, תני רישא דלא צריכה ותני סיפא דלא
צריכה *tani reisha d'lo tzricha v'tani seifa d'lo tzricha*? Why would it
take both cases superfluous clauses? This is not a storybook, this is
a הלכה *halakha*, and we're going... we want to, you know, why
would we throw in extra phrases if they actually confuse what the
halakhic issues are? So therefore there's no legitimate explanation if it's in
the רישא *reisha*, it's only because אני *ani* itself would not have
done the work. And I agree with what, you know, Jenna said
and actually Jenna, it's... it's not only a question of how you
interpret the משנה *Mishnah*, it would be a question of the halakhically,
what would happen in the case of the רישא *reisha* that guy
number one said הריני נזיר ועלי לגלח *Hareini Nazir v'alai l'galeiach* and
somebody else said ואני עלי לגלח *v'ani alai l'galeiach*, okay, without the
ועלי לגלח *v'alai l'galeiach*, presumably they would only mean עלי לגלח *alai
l'galeiach*, without the ו' *vav*, you're... you are only saying the second
thing. Okay, but so it says, but if you just said ואני
*v'ani*, now we're saying the fact that the רישא *reisha* has a
second clause could only be because אני *ani* doesn't do the whole
work. Okay, so we will end here for now and the next
thing starts a whole another topic.